hello everyone i hope you're enjoying
bioc asia 2021 i'd like to thank the
conference organizers for inviting me to
speak today and while this isn't live
i'm very excited to be giving my first
keynote talk ever
my talk today is on bioconductor what
bioconductor is and how the core team
helps facilitate the project
so the first thing that surprised me
when i started going to more general r
and computing conferences was the
misconception that bioconductor was a
single r package and the bioconductor
project is much larger than a single
package bioconductor is an open source
and open development r package
repository system that focuses on
analysis comprehension and visualization
of genetic and genomic data
there are actually currently over 2000
software packages in addition to
specialized data experiment annotation
and workflow packages that are available
through the bioconductor interface
but bioconductor is more than just a
package repository system it really is a
well-developed organization and there
are many people involved with shaping
the direction of the project currently
there are three main advisory boards the
scientific technical and community
boards the scientific advisory board is
an invitation only board that provides
external guidance and oversight on the
scientific direction of the project
the technical and community advisory
boards however have open public
elections every spring for inclusion on
the board
the technical advisory board advises on
project and package level infrastructure
while the community advisory board is
really dedicated to developing enhancing
and diversifying the bioconductor
community
anyone can run for a position on these
two boards for the technical board it
may be useful to have some finer
knowledge of bioconductor and
programming or a specialized scientific
technology background but the community
board especially really wants to try and
be as diverse as possible and aims for a
mix of races ethnicity education level
and bioconductor experience so if you're
interested look for a call for
applications on the bioconductor support
site and community slack channel in
early spring
so thinking back on how this started
that bioconductor is more than just a
single package it's a package repository
and an organization but even more
importantly than that probably most
important it's a community so
bioconductor really aims at trying to
provide resources and infrastructure to
link experienced package maintainers
developers and users with the
inexperience to foster this
collaborative and welcoming community of
our bioconductor users
so how and where does this community
connect well there are a couple
different places most notably the
bioconductor support site the community
slack channels and numerous conference
workshops and training events that
happen through the year and also a newly
developed mentoring chip program and i
can just take you briefly through each
of those right now
the bioconductor support site is the
first place many users go to ask
questions and get advice on analysis or
to troubleshoot using bioconductor
packages
this support site is specialized to
bioconductor package questions and every
maintainer that submits a package to
bioconductor is required to sign up so
that if an ask question gets tagged with
their package name they would be
notified
there are thousands of users on here and
it can be a great resource to tap into
community knowledge and experience
so you can search by clicking on a
package tag or you could go to the tags
tab and search for a package to see what
already existing posts and questions
are available
if you don't see anything relevant to
what you need you can always post a new
question by clicking on the ask a
questions tab
make sure to have an informative title
and be sure to tag any relevant packages
that the question relates to in the post
tags
the body uses markdown or plain text or
html if you're having issues or errors
running code be sure to post as much of
the code example in the code section and
always include the platform and version
of r and bioconductor you are using so
we can tailor the responses
appropriately
the bioconductor team also uses the news
feature to post important announcements
for releases packages conferences
elections and other such news events
there's also the bioconductor community
slack channel and i really encourage
everyone to join the channel as it is
great for conversation there are a
number of specialized channels that may
be useful for a very particular
discussion like microbiome metabolomics
a proteomics channel
we also have channels to ask about core
infrastructure pieces that we'll discuss
a little bit later on but channels like
the bioc builds for build system
questions or biosee hubs for questions
unlike experiment hub annotation hub or
bioc file cache
there are a number of conferences
workshops and training events throughout
the year there's a bioconductor event
calendar off the main website that
anyone can submit bioconductor related
events to advertise
anyone is welcome to submit event
for inclusion on the page either by
emailing events at bioconductor.org
or we're working on a forum version that
should be available soon
minimum requirements for an event is a
relevance to bioconductor and a
willingness to adhere to the
bioconductor code of conduct
conferences are always a good time and a
great way to meet other members of the
community and network hopefully you are
all enjoying yourselves here at bioc
asia which has become an annual event
there's also the annual maine bios
conference normally held in the united
states in late summer
and the annual eurobiose conference and
the next currently one scheduled is for
march 2022
in recent years we are excited to see
initiatives in other countries as well
that bioconductor is glad to send
representatives and be a part of
the community of bioinformatics software
developers in mexico and latin america
have started organizing yearly week-long
workshops and various conference and
workshops throughout the year to aid in
development of the spanish-speaking
armed bioconnector community
and the h3a bionet and h3a africa
launched a series of workshops and
webinars to help advance the african
coding and research communities which
bioconductor took part in also
these again are just a few of the many
workshops webinars and training
opportunities launched around the world
throughout the year and we are really
excited to see that the bioconnector
community is growing and that we can be
a part of research worldwide
so those are some great resources to
connect to the community but now i want
to take it back to this slide on
organization just for a second because
we skipped over the last entry the core
team
the core team plays a vital role in the
functionality of the project it's a
small dedicated group of developers that
help develop maintain and enhance core
packages and project level
infrastructure
so what does that really mean i get the
feeling that most people think that the
core team only takes care of core
packages and package maintenance but we
really do so much more than that we
talked about bioconductor being a
project there's a lot of infrastructure
pieces that are in place to make the
project function so thinking about the
resources we just went over what core
infrastructure is involved that the core
team maintains
so first there's the main website
bioconductor.org
the core team is responsible for updates
and website upkeep there's an entire
code base for the website and the
website is regenerated about every 20
minutes to make sure that there is
constant up-to-date information
similarly there's a code base for the
support site website we thankfully have
support and help from the biostars that
our support site is modeled after and in
particular an attay that assists but we
still have core team involvement in the
upkeep and maintenance of that site
there's also monitoring and answering
questions that appear on the community
slack channels many times resulting in
follow-up and investigation of issues
comments and concerns
and many core team members participate
in presenting material for conferences
and workshops
there's also normally components of the
conference like specialized web pages
systems for hosting workshops and having
computer environments for participants
that the core team also helps manage and
facilitate so hopefully you can already
see the importance of this back-end
infrastructure so continuing on i want
to think about bioconductor from two
perspectives a user and a developer and
along the way we'll discuss additional
important project infrastructure that
the core team helps develop maintain and
enhance to try to provide a good
experience to the community
so thinking about a user how does a user
interact with bioconductor traditionally
i think most users were using our
terminal or rstudio which is still
highly popular and widely utilized but
there are also newer available
technologies and projects like using
docker images or cloud-based initiatives
like the anvil project that allow a
different user experience
for our terminal and rstudio users
there's a cram package bioc manager that
is downloaded installed from cran and
provides access to all packages in
bioconductor and crayon repositories the
anvil which stands for analysis
visualization and informative lab space
is an nhgri project it provides a secure
cloud-based computing environment for
analysis i will not go into detail here
about anvil and docker images but i
encourage everyone to attend natashas
talk where i believe some of these
concepts and resources will be covered i
will mention that the anvil bioconductor
package provides a different install
function designed specifically for use
with the bioconductor docker images and
the anvil computing space that can
provide fast binary package installation
why is this significant well some
packages require compilation which can
take several seconds package binaries
are pre-compiled allowing for a near
instantaneous installation the
limitation of binaries is that package
binaries are specific to the system
configuration to which they were
generated which is why they're only
available for use with the docker
another important concept for users
especially new users is how to find
packages of interest in bios manager
there's a function available that shows
a listing of all available packages or
you could use a search term to find
packages but that assumes some a priori
knowledge the bioc views page and
package landing pages can be really
useful for finding packages
off the bioconductor.org home page
there's a link to available software
packages this takes you to what we call
our bioseed views page and includes
software annotation experiment and
workflow packages books are coming soon
you can either search for terms of
interest like single cell or proteomics
to get a list of packages or if you know
a package name you can search for it
specifically like genomic ranges or
summarized experiment
the rank ordering is in order of most
downloaded to lease downloaded and if
you click on a package name it takes you
to a bioconductor's package landing page
the page has badges to indicate package
health and information on the package
like the description documentation what
package dependencies or reverse
dependencies there are
and in the bottom a link to download the
package directly instead of through bioc
manager access to the code base in
git.bioconductor.org
and package download statistics
probably the most helpful on this page
is the package documentation that a user
can browse through before downloading a
package to see if it's appropriate for
their type of analysis
so before switching to a developer's
point of view let's revisit the core
team and in these few concepts for users
what sort of infrastructure is required
in the background
so there's obviously some package
maintenance with regard to bioc manager
anvil anvil specific packages and
bioseat views packages
there's a concept of a daily build of
all bioconductor packages so that
they're available through the bioc
manager install function
there's generation and upkeep of docker
images so bioconductor docker images for
both release and develop branches and an
anvil specific docker image that needs
to be submitted to the anvil platform
there's also the binary package
generation for those provide packages
provided through anvil install
and then there's the website code and
website interaction so that you could
see that biosea views page and package
landing pages and the constant
regeneration of the website to make sure
that all that information stays up to
date to the latest
and then at the bottom of the packing
landing pages i mentioned it briefly but
there's package download statistics that
get calculated for each package as well
so again hopefully that you can see
while it may seem like trivial and basic
functionality that there's a lot that
needs to be in place behind the scenes
for everything to function properly and
interact properly
so the core team has a subset of
packages that are considered core
packages and core team maintained but
most of the packages in bioconductor are
community contributed
anyone from the community is welcome to
develop and submit a package to
bioconductor there are certain specific
package requirements that should be
implemented when developing and a
package will undergo a review process
once a package is accepted then it's
added to the daily builder and available
through bioc manager install
so package specific requirements can be
found at contributions.bioconnector.org
and the developer section of the main
website we are in the process of moving
information from the developer section
of the website to the
contributions.bioconductor.org location
so eventually all the information will
be in one location
but let's go over some of the key
concepts that should be implemented when
developing a package
one of the main things is reusing or
extending existing classes and using the
well-developed import and export methods
for certain data types bioconductor has
the concept of interoperability so if a
user wants to use one package to import
a different normalize and a third to
visualize the manipulation of data from
one package to the next should be
minimal if not eliminated completely for
the user so ideally the output of one
should be the input to another
this is why we like to emphasize using
or extending any of the existing class
structures another good practice worth
mentioning is the caching of web-based
data when possible this way if a user is
without internet or requests the same
file from a website or a website is
temporary unavailable they don't have to
re-download and could potentially use a
previously downloaded version instead of
having to wait for the internet or
re-download data
another good practice is implementing
unit tests it's strongly recommended
while tests can seem burdensome if added
to the development process early it can
actually aid in development so testing
for things like edge cases and having
both positive and negative tests can
ensure proper proper functionality
biggest thing that bioconductor is also
going to insist upon is a really
detailed vignette with runnable code
examples so vignettes are compiled when
built so it can also help ensure proper
functioning code but we like detailed
vignettes because ideally this gives
your users
an understanding of the package and the
unique functionality that the package
provides and these are just a few
concepts of the many that you'll find on
this
contributions.bioconductor.org page
so once a package is developed a user
then submits to the bioconductor new
submission tracker on github
there's some useful information on the
home page about what to expect and how
to submit related or dependent packages
but to submit a new issue you go to open
a new issue under bioconductor
contributions the title should be your
package name
all packages currently require a github
repository location and the link should
be updated pointing to this location
a package then is an awaiting moderation
stage
a reviewer will be assigned and the
package added to our
get.bioconductor.org location and a
build triggered on all three major os
platforms linux mac and windows
once a package is building and checking
without error the reviewer will do an
in-depth review of the package and offer
comments suggestions or request changes
consistent with bioconductor package
requirements
there's an open dialogue in the review
process open to the community and
governed by the bioconductor code of
conduct
once a package is accepted it's added to
the nightly daily builder
bioconductor uses get for version
control of package source code
bioconductor builds only from
get.bioconductor.org and users must push
changes to this location to propagate
them to users
from a few times a week to daily the
bioconductor builders will do a get
clone a version of the package and then
do an r command install r command build
and r command check
if the package installs builds and
checks cleanly and has a valid version
bump for changes the package is
propagated and becomes available through
the bioc manager install function
maintainers can find the build reports
from the main website in the lower right
corner marked build reports this page
indicates how frequently the builds take
place
if we click on browse for any of the
build reports you'll get a list of every
bioconductor package and the status
through each stage the top of the page
has a time stamp to indicate when it was
generated and each package has
information on the version git commit
and get date that the builder used for
that report
you can click on any stage indicator for
more information and results
so what infrastructure is needed for
everything just discussed for submitting
a package
well there's evaluating and updating of
the package guidelines
there's the code that interacts with the
package submission process on github and
code specific to the new submission
process on each of the three develop
builders
the core team also participates
currently in package reviews for new
submissions
there is facilitating the entire
bioconductor get ecosystem which
includes the
get.bioconductor.org main repository
location for all of the bioconductor
packages a git contributions app that
manages ssh credentials of users
get a light application that manages
which users have access to which
packages and gut hooks that respond to
different triggering events
there's also the bioconductor build
system called the bbs which is a large
undertaking of the core team there are
minimally six build machines that
require system administration and the
underlying code base on each to handle
the get clone the r command install the
r command build the r command check the
package propagation and the generation
of the build reports
and there's minimally six builders
because for both the bioconductor
release and bioconductor devel branches
we cover the three main os platforms of
mac linux and windows
so briefly i wanted to also touch upon
why bioconductor has a release in a
devel branch bioconductor is closely
associated with r
most years in spring r has a release
bioconductor then needs to update which
version of r is being used for packages
to insured continued proper
functionality
bioconductor has two releases of gear a
spring and a fall
where the devel branch is released and
becomes the new release
from roughly late april and early may
when the new version of r is released
both the bioconductor release and devel
branch use that stapled release version
of r or our patched version
in fall normally late october early
november bioconductor does a second
release
at this time the bioconductor release
branch still uses that stable rr patch
version but the devel bioconductor
branch switches to use r devel in
preparation for the next r release in
spring
having a devel branch allows maintainers
to adapt to changes in base r as well as
changes in any other dependent packages
that they may have and then have minimal
disruption or downtime to the end user
bioconductor encourage package
maintainers to enhance and make major
changes on the development branch and
restrict changes on the release branch
to minor bug corrections again also
reasoning that there would be a place
for development and potential breakage
without affecting the end users
the core team is always extremely busy
during release time and with release
related tasks it involves updating
versions of r and bioconductor on
minimumly the six builders
emailing maintainers that ignored the
build failure notifications to try and
fix their packages to avoid deprecation
and removal from bioconductor
reviewing the influx of newly submitted
packages for inclusion
fixing or modifying any core packages
that require such attention adding
release related annotation resources
creating new branches on
get.bioconductor.org for all the
packages for the new release
and collating all the news files from
packages to generate the release
announcement
there is another key infrastructure
piece that the core team maintains that
has gained increasing popularity in
recent years the concept of the
bioconductor hubs annotation hub and
experiment hub
as a brief background git does not allow
large files and our current git system
does not support get lfs which means
there has to be an alternative way to
provide large data sets to users
bioconductor insists data to be hosted
on a secure public or institutional
server like zenodo amazon s3 buckets
microsoft azure among other trusted
sites or direct access to web resources
or databases if available like ensemble
or ncbi
rather than privately hosting data on
say a github or dropbox
if you're developing a package we
encourage a discussion about data
hosting on other platforms on the
bioslee
dash devel
r-projects.org developers mailing list
if a maintainer does not have access to
such a resource bioconductor provides an
amazon s3 bucket for use
we are however actively investigating a
migration of location from amazon s3 to
microsoft azure
developers can download resources
directly from the trusted sites
but must implement a caching mechanism
in the background and we highly
recommend the bioconductor core package
bioc file cache
the other alternative to downloading
directly and implementing bios you file
cache is to list the data in the
annotation hub or experiment hub
the annotation hub and the experiment
hub are databases with references to the
external data for download
the hub interfaces provide a querying
mechanism on metadata provided at
inclusion of the data into the database
when using the hub interface for
download it already uses bioc file cache
as a caching mechanism so a maintainer
does not have to implement it themselves
the other advantage to listing the data
in the hubs is the findability of
resources outside of r or outside the
use of the associated bioconductor
package
there are bioconductor core packages
experiment hub and annotation hub that
can be queried for data of different
types or from different sources
the resources can be searched either
through a query performed within r or
investigation through the hub apis and
annotationhub.bioconductor.org or
experimenthub.bioconductor
the api is admittedly a little crude and
we are working on a revamp there's also
a shiny version to query hub resources
that has been developed and should be
announced soon
the query function in r will take a list
of terms and return resources matching
search criteria for example you can see
we queried here for ensembl gtf release
103 and homo sapiens which returned four
results
a single bracket using the ahid of
interest will give more information on
the resource and a double bracket will
download and cache the resource
the requirement to add data to the hubs
is a package that is already or will be
submitted to bioconductor that includes
an inst metadata.csv file with metadata
for the resources that will be added to
the database
and an in-script directory with files
that indicate how the data was generated
and relevant source information
the vignette creating a hub package
experiment hub or annotation hub in the
core package hub pub describes this in
more detail
other questions can be directed to the
hubs at bioconductor.org email
the hubs currently involve a lot of
interaction from the core team we are
working on making enhancements and
restructure to try to make it simpler
and easier to submit and maintain hub
data with limited core team interaction
currently when data is submitted to the
hubs a core team member will evaluate
the data and metadata provided
if needed assist with uploading data to
the bioconductor provided location again
currently that's an amazon s3 bucket but
that could change
and update the database for the metadata
provided so the metadata is available
through the query functions
additionally core team maintenance of
the hubs includes managing server code
on the amazon web service ec2 instances
that hosts the website and api endpoints
for both hubs and general core package
maintenance of the relevant core
packages experiment hub annotation hub
bioc file cache experiment hub data
annotation hub data and hubpub
so there are still other core related
tasks and infrastructure that we just
haven't had time to touch on things like
the amazon web service resources that we
utilize and the microsoft azure project
resources
but
hopefully this gave everyone an idea of
how much the core team supports in
addition to just general core package
health and development
so with that i would like to thank the
conference organizers for inviting me to
speak it really has been an honor and
thank you to my fellow core team members
i appreciate all the work and effort we
all put into keeping the project moving
forward
and most of all a thank you to the
bioconductor community bioconductor
would not be successful without the
contributions of all of you and whether
you're a first time user or a long-time
contributor we really hope that you
found a welcoming and helpful community
so please feel free to send me any
questions to my email or on the
community slack if anyone has any
questions about this presentation
thank you cheers
you